Sir John Simeon Correspondence
Sir John Simeon Correspondence
1824-1870
Simeon, John, Sir, 1815-1870.
0.75 linear ft.
Papers of the British politician. Simeon, 3rd baronet and eldest son of Sir Richard Godwin Simeon, was born and lived most of his life at Swainston on the Isle of Wight. Succeeding to the title in 1854, Simeon, following a career in the Navy, served as a Member of Parliament from the Isle of Wight from 1847 to 1851, and again between 1865 and 1870. Nearly 350 incoming letters to Sir John Simeon from prominent Victorians, including literary figures, politicians, religious leaders, scholars and statesmen.
146313
Biographical History
Sir John Simeon (1815-1870) was born and lived most of his life at Swainston on the Isle of Wight. Third baronet and eldest son of Sir Richard Godwin Simeon, Sir John Simeon succeeded to the title in 1854. Following a career in the Navy, Simeon served as a Member of Parliament for the Isle of Wight from 1847 to 1851, and again between 1865 and 1870.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Sir John Simeon Correspondence comprises nearly 350 incoming letters.
Organized alphabetically, the collection begins with 9 incoming letters written between 1824 and 1846 to John's father, Sir Richard Simeon. Among this group are letters from political and religious figures, including an extensive missive from social reformer and abolitionist William Wilberforce concerning slavery in the West Indies.
The remainder of the letters span 1854 through 1870 and reflect Simeon's prominence in the social, political, and artistic circles on the Isle of Wight. For a time the only Roman Catholic Member of Parliament, Simeon, who was closely associated with the Oxford Movement, numbered among his correspondents many of the Victorian era's most influential politicians, statesmen (Frederick Temple Blackwood, Henry Bruce, Edward Cardwell, Hugh Childers, William Gladstone, George Goschen, George Lyttleton, William Monsell) and religious leaders (George Granville Bradley, Henry Manning, Arthur Stanley, William Ward, Samuel Wilberforce).
A classical scholar himself, Simeon's correspondents also included antiquarians (Frederic Madden, Thomas Wright), authors (Alexander Beresford-Hope, George Brodrick, Charles Kingsley, William Lecky, Anthony Sterling, Philip Henry Stanhope, William Stirling-Maxwell, George Venables), men of letters (James Froude, Theodore Martin, Richard Monckton Milnes), and scholars (Stephen de Vere, Benjamin Jowett, James Lacaita, Thomas May). With the arrival of Alfred Tennyson at Farringford, near Swainston, Simeon's circle of acquaintances broadened to include literary figures (William Allingham, Robert Browning, Pauline Craven, Aubrey de Vere, Georgiana Fullerton, Frederick Locker-Lampson, Charles Merivale, Caroline Norton, Laurence Oliphant, Coventry Patmore, Anthony Trollope).
Simeon's correspondents also included representatives of the visual and performing arts, including illustrators (Richard Doyle, Edward Lear), painters (William Boxall, Francis Grant, William Holman Hunt, Edwin Landseer, Frederic Leighton), photographers (Julia Margaret Cameron), sculptors (George Frederick Watts, Thomas Woolner), actresses (Helena Faucit Martin), and musicians (Charles Hamilton Aide, Charles Halle, Henry Russell).
While the Simeon letters are rich in associations with prominent Victorians, they are perhaps most valuable for their illumination of the intellectual, political, and social life which flourished on the Isle of Wight during that period.
Arrangement of the Collection
Letters are divided into those of Richard Simeon and of John Simeon; within that they are arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- British; Simeon, John, Sir, 1815-1870.; Simeon, Richard Godwin, Sir, 1784-1854.; Legislators -- England -- Isle of Wight.; Politicians -- England -- Isle of Wight.; Catholics -- Great Britain.; Great Britain -- Politics and government -- 19th century.; Great Britain -- Social life and customs -- 19th century.; Great Britain -- Intellectual life -- 19th century.; Isle of Wight (England) -- History -- 19th century.; Isle of Wight (England) -- Social life and customs -- 19th century.; Isle of Wight (England) -- Political activity -- 19th century.; Isle of Wight (England) -- Politics and government.; Isle of Wight (England) -- Intellectual life -- 19th century.; Legislators.; Politicians.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Richard Simeon correspondence
  - Graham, James Robert George, 1845; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Grey, George, 1846; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Harris, James Edward, See Malmesbury, James Edward Harris
  - Malmesbury, James Edward Harris, 1826; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Taylor, Herbert, 1824; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Wellesley, Arthur, Duke of Wellington, See Wellington, Arthur Wellesley
  - Wellington, Arthur Wellesley, 1845; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Wilberforce, Samuel, 1843; undated; 2 letters (Box 1)
  - Wilberforce, William, 1826; 2 letters (Box 1)
- John Simeon correspondence (Box 1)
  - Adderley, Charles Bowyer, undated; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Aide, Charles Hamilton, See Aide, Hamilton
  - Aide, Hamilton, 1869; undated; 3 letters (Box 1)
  - Allingham, William, 1869; 2 letters (Box 1)
  - Arthur William Patrick Albert, Duke of Connaught and Strathearn, 1868; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Aumale, Henri d'Orleans, duc d', 1860; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Baker, Samuel White, 1869; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Ball, John, 1859; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Beresford-Hope, Alexander James Beresford, 1869?; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Blackwood, Frederick Temple, See Dufferin and Ava, Frederick Temple Blackwood
  - Boxall, William, undated; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Bradley, George Granville, 1865; undated; 2 letters (Box 1)
  - Brodrick, George Charles, undated; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Browning, Robert, 1867; 1870; 2 letters (Box 1)
  - Bruce, Henry Austin, 1868; 1869?; 3 letters (Box 1)
  - Cameron, Julia Margaret, 1868; 1870; 2 letters (Box 1)
  - Cardwell, Edward Cardwell, 1865; 1870; 5 letters (Box 1)
  - Carlingford, Chichester Samuel Parkinson-Fortescue, 1863; 1865,; undated; 3 letters (Box 1)
  - Carmichael, James Robert, 1854; 1865,; 1869; 4 letters (Box 1)
  - Carnarvon, Henry Howard Molyneux, 1857; 1863,; 1864; 5 letters (Box 1)
  - Cavendish, Richard, 1861; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Cayley, George John, undated; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Chance, J. H., 1865; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Childers, Hugh Culling Eardley, 1867; 1869,; 1870; 4 letters; 1 outgoing letter (Box 1)
  - Circourt, Adolphe de, 1866; undated; 3 letters (Box 1)
  - Clifford, Charles Cavendish, 1860; 1865,; undated; 5 letters (Box 1)
  - Clifford, Charles J. (or T.), 1862; 2 letters (Box 1)
  - Connaught and Strathearn, Duke of, See Arthur William Patrick Albert, Duke of Connaught and Strathearn
  - Cowper, William Francis, See Mount-Temple, William Francis Cowper-Temple
  - Craven, Pauline Marie Armande Aglae, 1868; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - De Montalembert, Charles Forbes, See Montalembert, Charles Forbes
  - De Vere, Aubrey Thomas, 1853; 1854,; 1858,; 1860; 7 letters (Box 1)
  - De Vere, Stephen Edward, 1860; 1865?,; undated; 6 letters (Box 1)
  - D'Orleans, Henri, See Aumale, Henri d'Orleans, duc d'
  - Doyle, Francis Hastings Charles, undated; 2 letters (Box 1)
  - Doyle, Henry Edward, 1851; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Doyle, Richard, undated; 2 letters (Box 1)
  - Dufferin, Frederick Temple Blackwood, See Dufferin and Ava, Frederick Temple Blackwood
  - Dufferin and Ava, Frederick Temple Blackwood, 1866; 1869,; 1870,; undated; 5 letters (Box 1)
  - Elcho, See Wemyss, Francis Wemyss-Charteris Douglas
  - Enfield, Edward (?), 1865; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Erskine May, Thomas see, See May, Thomas Erskine
  - Estcourt, Edgar Edmund, 1861; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Eversley, Charles Shaw-Lefevre, 1857; 1859-1860; 1863-1866,; 1869; 18 letters (Box 1)
  - Farnborough, Thomas Erskine May, See May, Thomas Erskine
  - Faucit, Helena Saville, See Martin, Helena Faucit Saville
  - Forbes, Charles, See Montalembert, Charles Forbes
  - Forster, William Edward, 1865; undated; 2 letters (Box 1)
  - Fortesque, Chichester Samuel, See Carlingford, Chichester Samuel Parkinson-Fortescu
  - Fowler, John, 1870; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Froude, James Anthony, 1858; undated; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Fullerton, Georgiana, undated; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Galton, Douglas Strutt, 1865; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Gladstone, William Ewart, 1865; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Gordon, H. P.(?), 1868; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Goschen, George Joachim Goschen, 1868; undated; 5 letters (Box 1)
  - Grant, Francis, undated; 2 letters (Box 1)
  - Grant-Duff, Mountstuart Elphinstone, 1870; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Granville, Granville George Levenson-Gower, 1857 (or 1859); 1870; 5 letters (Box 1)
  - Grey, George, 1857; 1865; 2 letters (Box 1)
  - Gully, James Manby, 1869; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Halle, Charles, 1868; 4 letters (Box 1)
  - Harman, R., 1865; 1869; 2 letters (Box 1)
  - Head, Edmund Walker, 1867; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Herbert, Henry Howard Molyneux, See Carnarvon, Henry Howard Molyneux
  - Hope, Alexander James Beresford, See Beresford-Hope, Alexander James Beresford
  - Hope-Scott, James Robert, 1860; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Houghton, Richard Monckton Milnes, 1858; 1860,; 1870,; undated; 8 letters, 1 fragment (Box 1)
  - Houseman, Henry, 1867; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Hunt, William Holman, 1864; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Iddesleigh, Stafford Henry Northcote, 1867; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Jowett, Benjamin, 1869; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Kinglake, Alexander William, 1857; 1859,; 1863,; 1869; 4 letters (Box 1)
  - Kingsley, Charles, 1862; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Kingsley, George Henry, undated; 2 letters (Box 1)
  - Knatchbull-Hugesson, Edward Hugesson, 1867; 2 letters (Box 1)
  - Lacaita, James Phillip, 1869-1870; 4 letters (Box 1)
  - Landseer, Edwin Henry, 1869; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Lear, Edward, 1867-1869; undated; 5 letters, 1 drawing (Box 1)
  - Lecky, William Edward Hartpole, undated; 2 letters (Box 1)
  - Lefevre, Charles Shaw, See Eversley, Charles Shaw-Lefevre
  - Leighton, Frederic Leighton, See Leighton of Stretton, Frederic Leighton
  - Leighton of Stretton, Frederic Leighton, undated; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Leveson-Gower, Georgiana Charlotte, See Fullerton, Georgiana
  - Leveson-Gower, Granville George see, See Granville, Granville George Leveson-Gower
  - Locker-Lampson, Frederick, 1864; 1866,; 1869; 4 letters (Box 1)
  - Lyttleton, George William, 1857; 1860,; 1862,; 1869; includes one letter to R. Harman, 2 to R. Cavendish; 10 letters, (Box 1)
  - Madden, Frederic, 1858; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Manners, John James Robert, 1868; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Manning, Henry Edward, 1851?; 1854,; 1855,; 1857?,; 1859,; 1860; 13 letters (Box 1)
  - Martin, Helena Faucit Saville, undated; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Martin, Theodore, 1870?; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Maxwell, Caroline Elizabeth Sarah Sheridan Norton, See Norton, Caroline Sheridan
  - Maxwell, William Stirling, See Stirling-Maxwell, William
  - May, Thomas Erskine, 1868; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Merivale, Charles, undated; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Milman, Henry Hart, 1857; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Milnes, Richard Monckton, See Houghton, Richard Monckton Milnes
  - Molyneux, Henry Howard, See Carnarvon, Henry Howard Molyneux
  - Monsell, William, 1860; 6 letters (Box 1)
  - Montalembert, Charles Forbes, 1865; 1868,; 1869; 3 letters (Box 1)
  - Motley, John Lothrop, undated; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Mount-Temple, William Francis Cowper-Temple, 1868; 1869,; undated; 3 letters (Box 1)
  - Murchison, Roderick Impey, 1865?; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Murray, John, 1860; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Northcote, Stafford Henry, See Iddesleigh, Stafford Henry Northcote
  - Norton, Caroline Sheridan, undated; 2 letters (Box 1)
  - Oliphant, Laurence, undated; 2 letters (Box 1)
  - Orleans, Henri d', See Aumale, Henri d'Orleans, duc d'
  - Owen, Richard, undated; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Palgrave, Francis Turner, 1863; 1 letter (Box 2)
  - Palmer, Roundell, See Selborne, Roundell Palmer
  - Parkinson-Fortescue, Chichester Samuel, See Carlingford, Chichester Samuel Parkinson-Fortescue
  - Patmore, Coventry Kersey Dighton, 1856-1857; 1859-1860,; undated; 12 letters (Box 2)
  - Pollen, John Hungerford, 1860; 1 letter (Box 2)
  - Prinsep, Henry Thoby, undated; 1 letter (Box 2)
  - Prinsep, Sara, 1865; 1 letter (Box 2)
  - Russell, Elizabeth Anne, 1868; 1 letter (Box 2)
  - Russell, Henry, undated; 1 letter (Box 2)
  - Russell, John Russell, 1851; 1 letter (Box 2)
  - Seely, Mary, 1865; 1 letter (Box 2)
  - Selborne, Roundell Palmer, 1865; 1 letter (Box 2)
  - Selfe, Henry James Seife, 1867; 1 letter (Box 2)
  - Shaw-LeFevre, Charles, See Eversley, Charles Shaw-LeFevre
  - Shelley, Frances Winckley, date illegible; 1 letter (Box 2)
  - Stanhope, Philip Henry, 1868; 1 letter (Box 2)
  - Stanley, Arthur Penrhyn, 1865; 1870,; undated; 9 letters (Box 2)
  - Sterling, Anthony Coningham, 1862; 1870; 2 letters (Box 2)
  - Stirling-Maxwell, Caroline Elizabeth Sarah Sheridan Norton, See Norton, Caroline Sheridan
  - Stirling-Maxwell, William, 1862; 1868-1870; 5 letters (Box 2)
  - Taylor, Henry, 1856; 1 letter (Box 2)
  - Taylor, Tom, undated; 1 letter (Box 2)
  - Tennyson, Alfred Tennyson, 1860; 1865,; 1868,; undated; 6 letters (Box 2)
  - Tennyson, Emily Sellwood Tennyson, 1860-1861; 1865,; 1867,; 1869; 8 letters (Box 2)
  - Trevelyan, George Otto, 1867?; 1 letter (Box 2)
  - Trollope, Anthony, undated; 1 letter (Box 2)
  - Van de Weyer, Sylvain, undated; 1 letter (Box 2)
  - Venables, George Stovin, undated; 1 letter (Box 2)
  - Ward, William George, 1854; 1857,; 1860,; 1865,; 1868,; undated; 12 letters (Box 2)
  - Watts, George Frederick, undated; 1 letter (Box 2)
  - Wemyss, Francis Wemyss-Charteris Douglas, 1859; 1 letter (Box 2)
  - Wetherell, T. F., 1865; 1 letter (Box 2)
  - Wilberforce, Samuel, 1862; undated; 2 letters (Box 2)
  - Woolner, Thomas, 1859; 1862-1865,; 1867-1869; 8 letters (Box 2)
  - Wright, Thomas, 1858; 2 letters (Box 2)
  - Wynne, Charles, 1860; undated; 2 letters (Box 2)
  - Wyvill, Marmaduke, 1866; 1 letter (Box 2)
- Partial identification or unidentified
  - C.W.F., 1869; 3 letters (from Paris) (Box 2)
  - Emanuel, 1865; 1 letter (Box 2)
  - Grey (?), 1864-1865; 2 letters (Box 2)
  - Grosvenor, undated; 1 letter (Box 2)
  - Wodehouse, 1869; 1 letter (Box 2)
  - Unidentified, 1858; 1 letter (Box 2)
  - Unidentified, 1866; 5 letters (Box 2)
  - Unidentified, 1867; 1 letter (Box 2)